Arna Bontemps Papers
Arna Bontemps Papers
1927-1968
Bontemps, Arna, 1902-1973.
42 linear ft.
Correspondence, manuscript plays, stories, songs, speeches, and book manuscripts and galley proofs.
143290
Biographical History
African-American poet, critic, playwright, novelist, author of children's books, librarian.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
Spanning 1888 to 1997, the Arna Wendell Bontemps Papers comprises correspondence, writings and memorabilia of the educator, historian, librarian and Harlem Renaissance poet, novelist, playwright, and critic (1902-1973). While documenting Bontemps 21-year career as librarian at Fisk University, the collection also illuminates the life and work of this early chronicler of African-American culture. With the exception of some late 19th century secondary sources associated with Bontemps' research, the bulk of the original documentation dates from 1935 forward.
Arranged alphabetically, the Correspondence-Subject Files (Boxes 1-30) contains incoming letters and outgoing carbons as well as publicity, programs, and other printed material relating to lecture engagements, play productions, and writing projects. Correspondents whose letters are of greatest depth and duration include Paul Breman, publisher of Bontemps' book of poetry, Personals; Anvil editor Jack Conroy, Bontemps' collaborator on They Seek a City and three children's books; playwright Owen Dodson, with whom Bontemps served on the American Film Center's Committee for Mass Communication in Race Relations; poet Countee Cullen, Bontemps' collaborator on the play "St. Louis Woman"; composer W. C. Handy, for whom Bontemps acted as ghost writer for his autobiography, Father of the Blues; literary agents Maxim Lieber and John B. Turner; and Harlem Renaissance critic and photographer Carl Van Vechten. Bontemps' other correspondents include artists (Aaron Douglas, Jacob Lawrence); civil rights activists (Julian Bond, Mary White Ovington, Mary Church Terrell, Walter White, Roy Wilkins); composers (Harold Arlen, Verna Arvey, Thomas A. Dorsey, Ulysses Kay, William Grant Still, John W. Work); critics (Herbert Hill, Nick Aaron Ford, John T. Frederick, Blyden Jackson, Alain Locke, J. Saunders Redding, Darwin Turner); editors and journalists (Horace R. Cayton, Frank M. Davis, Fuller W. Hoyt, Harold Jackman, Roi Ottley, George S. Schuyler); historians (August Meier, Lawrence Dunbar Reddick); juvenile literature authors (Erick Berry, Mari Evans, Florence Crannell Means, Milton Meltzer, Charlemae Rollins, Ellen Tarry); novelists (William Demby, Ralph Ellison, John O. Killens, Clarence Major, Alice Walker); playwrights (Georgia Douglas Johnson, Robert Lucas, Schuyler Watts); poets (Amiri Baraka, Gwendolyn Brooks, Sterling Brown, Lucille Clifton, Marcus Christian, Frank S. Horne, Melvin B. Tolson); and sociologists (C. Eric Lincoln, Ira DeAugustine Reid). Although not characterized by a large number of letters, the Correspondence-Subject Files relating to educator W.E.B. Du Bois, novelist Jean Toomer, poet and playwright Langston Hughes, and sociologist Charles S. Johnson constitutes a unique group of documents which includes third-party correspondence, printed material by and about these figures, and manuscript writings.
Organizational correspondence includes that of cultural associations (American Society of African Culture, Association for the Study of Negro Life and History, Inc.); educational institutions (Dillard University, Fisk University, George Peabody College for Teachers, University of California, University of Chicago); fraternal organizations (Omega Psi Phi, Sigma Pi Phi); newspapers (The Chicago Defender, The Chicago Sun, The Chicago Tribune, The New York Herald-Tribune); periodicals (Common Ground, The Crisis, Ebony, Negro Digest, The Saturday Review of Literature); publishers (American Book Company, Dodd, Mead & Company, Doubleday & Company, Follett Publishing Company, Grolier, Inc., Hill and Wang, Inc., Houghton Mifflin Company, McGraw-Hill Book Company, Macmillan Com pany, John C. Winston Company); professional organizations (American Library Association, Association for Childhood Education, Authors League of America, P.E.N.); religious groups (American Friends Service Committee, Seventh-day Adventists, the Methodist Church); and theatrical companies (Establishment Theatre Company, Inc., Karamu Theatre). Of particular interest among the organizational files are the materials relating to the Julius Rosenwald Fund, a philanthropic institution which awarded Bontemps a fellowship, and for which he later served on its selection committee.
Arranged by format, Writings (Boxes 31-76) includes research material, notes, drafts, manuscripts and/or published material for articles and essays, book reviews, books, play and radio scripts, poems, song lyrics, speeches and stories. Articles and essays range from biographical sketches ("Rock, Church, Rock") to medical pamphlets ("The Low-Down on TB"), personal reminiscences ("The Awakening: a Memoir") to professional publications ("Special Collections of Negroana"). As both a librarian and a creative writer, Bontemps was uniquely qualified (and therefore often called upon) to contribute to a variety of publications that included American Scholar, Arts in Childhood, Film News, The Message Magazine, Phylon, and Tomorrow. Reflecting his eclectic interests and extending them to the book format, Bontemps produced anthologies (The Book of Negro Folklore, Great Slave Narratives, The Poetry of the Negro); histories (They Seek a City, 100 Years of Negro Freedom); children's fiction (Lonesome Boy, Sam Patch, Slappy Hooper); juvenile biographies (George Washington Carver, Young Booker); novels (Chariot in the Sky, Drums at Dusk); and collections of his poems (Personals) and stories (The Old South). Written mostly as collaborative efforts, playscripts include "Creole Square" (with Schuyler Watts); "The Great Speckled Bird" (with Jack Conroy); "St. Louis Woman" (with Countee Cullen); and "When the Jack Hollers" and "Jubilee" (with Langston Hughes), the latter staged for the 1940 Negro Exposition in Chicago, and subsequently produced for radio broadcast. Spanning 1939 to 1966, the radio and television scripts document Bontemps' media appearances and book promotions. His close association with Harlem Renaissance figures, together with his practical knowledge of both librarianship and book publishing, brought Bontemps a steady barrage of invitations to deliver speeches at church services, public school assemblies, librarians' conferences, teachers' convocations, university seminars, and writers' symposiums. Characterized by an anecdotal prose style, Bontemps' stories aren't reliably distinguishable from his essays, at least one of which, "3 Pennies for Luck," was published as both fiction and non-fiction. Unpublished biography ("Young King Cole"), juvenile literature ("Bon-Bon Buddy"; "Boy of the Border"; "Tom-Tom Treasure"), novels ("The Chariot in the Cloud"; "Of Many Waters"; "Yielding Seed"); anthologies ("Rat Tales"; "Sugar Hill") and unfinished projects constitute Miscellaneous Writings.
Memorabilia (Boxes 77-85) includes address books, citations, financial material, clippings about Bontemps, reviews, travel-related items, including guidebooks and souvenirs, and research material, mostly printed, on Africa, civil rights in the U.S., and Langston Hughes. Periodical issues of The Colored American Magazine, The Crisis, The Messenger, Opportunity, and The Voice of the Negro, as well as small amount of ephemera, have been added to the Library's rare book collection.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Writings are subdivided by type (e.g, articles, book reviews) and within each subseries are arranged alphabetically by title. Memorabilia is arranged alphabetically by type.
Separated Material
A number of items, mostly issues of periodicals, were removed from the collection and transferred to Rare Books for cataloging, as follows:
The Colored American Magazine - 1901, Aug; 1906, Oct; 1909, May and Nov
The Crisis - 1926; 1927, Jan-Apr and June-Dec; 1928, Jan-Nov; 1929; 1930; 1931, Jan-Feb
The Messenger - 1925, Dec; 1926, Jan-June and Aug-Dec; 1927, Jan-Mar and May
National Negro Conference Proceedings - 1909 (1st)
Northwestern University on the Air: Of Men and Books - 1941, Nov. 18, "Negro Writers" (guest, Arna Bontemps); 1942, Nov. 18, "Children's Books and American Unity" (guest, Arna Bontemps); 1944, May 27, "Race Relations" (guest, Arna Bontemps)
Opportunity - 1925, Dec; 1926, Jul, Sep, Nov; 1928, Jan; 1942, Feb
Tops - Vol. 1, no. 2 (undated)
The Voice of the Negro - 1904 May
"Profiles of Black Achievement: Arna Bontmeps/Aaron Douglas" (Pleasantville, N.Y.: Guidance Associates, 1973) consisting of 2 filmstrips and 2 phonodiscs, with accompanying discussion guide
To locate these items, please refer to.
Subject and Genre Headings
Radicalism; Literature -- Children's; Literature -- American Fiction; Literature -- American Poetry; African Americans; Aaron, Stephen.; Algren, Nelson, 1909-1981.; Anderson, T. J. (Thomas Jefferson), 1928-; Arlen, Harold, 1905-1986.; Arvey, Verna, 1910-1987.; Asch, Moses.; Baraka, Amiri, 1934-2014.; Bayliss, John F.; Bond, Julian, 1940-2015.; Bontemps, Arna, 1902-1973.; Braithwaite, William Stanley, 1878-1962.; Breman, Paul.; Brooks, Gwendolyn, 1917-2000.; Brown, Sterling A., 1901-1989.; Burden, Jean.; Burroughs, Margaret Taylor, 1915-2010.; Campbell, E. Simms (Elmer Simms), 1906-1971.; Cayton, Horace R. (Horace Roscoe), 1903-1970.; Chapman, Abraham.; Christian, Marcus Bruce, 1900-1976.; Clarke, John Henrik, 1915-1998.; Conroy, Jack, 1898-1990.; Cullen, Countee, 1903-1946.; Cullen, Ida Mae Roberson.; Cuney, William Waring, 1906-1976.; Danner, Margaret.; Davis, Frank Marshall, 1905-1987.; Davis, Robert A.; Dawson, William L. (William Levi), 1886-1970.; Demby, William.; Dodson, Owen, 1914-1983.; Dover, Cedric.; Du Bois, W. E. B. (William Edward Burghardt), 1868-1963.; Edmonds, Randolph, 1900-1983.; Ellison, Ralph.; Emanuel, James A., 1921-2013.; Evans, Mari, 1923-; Fabre, Michel.; Fauset, Jessie Redmon.; Fields, Julia.; Frederick, John T. (John Towner), 1893-1975.; Gleason, Ralph J.; Handy, W. C. (William Christopher), 1873-1958.; Hill, Herbert, 1924-2004.; Hines, Carl Wendell.; Howland, Frances.; Hudson, David.; Hughes, Langston, 1902-1967.; Huntley, Leston.; Jackman, Harold, 1901-1961.; Jacobsen, Josephine.; Joans, Ted.; Johnson, Charles Spurgeon, 1893-1956.; Johnson, Georgia Douglas, 1886-1966.; Kay, Ulysses, 1917-1995.; Lawrence, Jacob, 1917-2000.; Locke, Alain, 1885-1954.; Major, Clarence.; Meadowcroft, Enid La Monte, 1898-1966.; Means, Florence Crannell, 1891-; Meltzer, Milton, 1915-2009.; Mitchell, Loften.; Moon, Bucklin, 1911-; Newsome, Effie Lee, 1885-1979.; Oden, Gloria.; Ottley, Roi, 1906-1960.; Ovington, Mary White, 1865-1951.; Palfi, Marion, 1907-1978.; Piquion, René.; Pool, Rosey E., 1905-1971.; Preece, Harold, 1906-; Preminger, Alex.; Randall, Dudley, 1914-2000.; Reynolds, Louis B. (Louis Bernard), 1917-1983.; Rosenwald, Lessing J. (Lessing Julius), 1891-1979.; Schuyler, George S. (George Samuel), 1895-1977.; Shute, Nevil, 1899-1960.; Still, William Grant, 1895-1978.; Stock, Mildred.; Tarry, Ellen, 1906-2008.; Terrell, Mary Church, 1863-1954.; Thompson, Era Bell.; Tolsin, Melvin Beaunorus.; Toomer, Marjorie Content.; Tunis, John Roberts, 1889-1975.; Turner, Darwin T., 1931-1991.; Turner, John B.; Van Vechten, Carl, 1880-1964.; White, Clarence Cameron, 1880-1960.; White, Walter, 1893-1955.; Work, John W. (John Wesley), 1901-1967.; Fisk University.; Federal Writers' Project.; African-American arts.; African American dramatists.; African American librarians.; African American intellectuals.; African American novelists.; African American poets.; African American Seventh-Day Adventists.; African Americans -- Biography.; African Americans -- Intellectual life.; African Americans -- Music.; African Americans in the performing arts.; American literature -- African American authors.; Authors, American -- 20th century.; Children's literature -- Authorship.; Harlem Renaissance -- Archival resources.; United States -- Civilization -- African American influences.; United States -- Race relations.; Correspondence.; Galley proofs.; Manuscripts for publication.; Scripts (documents); Songs (document genre); Speeches (documents); Authors.; Librarians.; Playwrights.; Poets.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Arna W. Bontemps, 1965-1973, and Mrs. Alberta Bontemps, 1998.
Inventory
- Correspondence-Subject Files
  - A, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Aaron, Stephen (Box 1)
  - Abrahams, Peter (Box 1)
  - Abrahamson, Julia (Box 1)
  - Abramson, Ben (Box 1)
  - Adoff, Arnold (Box 1)
  - Afro-American Newspapers (Box 1)
  - Agricultural and Technical College of North Carolina, See Turner, Darwin.
  - Alabama State College (Box 1)
  - Aladdin Books (Box 1)
  - Alba, Nanina (Box 1)
  - Alexander, Margaret Walker, See Walker, Margaret.
  - Alexander, Sally (Mrs. Ernest Raymond Alexander) (Box 1)
  - Algren, Nelson (Box 1)
  - Allen, Samuel W. (Box 1)
  - Alliance Productions, Inc., See Salisbury, Leah.
  - American Book Company, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - American Film Center, Inc. (Box 1)
    See also Dodson, Owen.
  - American Folklore Society (Box 1)
  - American Friends Service Committee (Box 1)
  - American Library Association, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - American Negro Exposition admission pass (Box 2)
  - The American Negro Reference Book, See Phelps-Stokes Fund.
  - The American Scholar (Box 2)
  - American Society of African Culture, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - American Studies Association (Box 2)
  - Ames, Elizabeth, See Yaddo.
  - Amos, Preston E. (Box 2)
  - Anderson, Margaret, See Common Ground.
  - Anderson, Thomas Jefferson (Box 2)
  - Andrews, Regina (Box 2)
  - Andric, Dragoslav (Box 2)
  - Archer, Leonard Courtney (Box 2)
  - Archon Books (Box 2)
  - Arkansas Teachers Association (Box 2)
  - Arlen, Harold
    - "Blues-Opera" (based on "St. Louis Woman"), manuscript (Box 2)
    - "Free and Easy" (based on "St. Louis Woman"), manuscript program (Box 2)
  - Arvey, Verna (Box 2)
  - Arvin, Newton (Box 2)
  - Asch, Moses (Box 2)
  - Associated Negro Press, Inc., See Barnett, Claude A..
  - Association for Childhood Education (Box 3)
  - Association for the Study of Negro Life and History, Inc. (Box 3)
  - Atkins, Russell (Box 3)
  - The Atlantic Monthly/Atlantic Monthly Press (Box 3)
  - Aubert, Alvin (Box 3)
  - Authors League of America, 1937-1968; undated; 5 folders (Box 3)
  - B, 1 folder (Box 3)
  - Bailey, Pearl (Box 3)
  - Baker, John (Box 3)
  - Banks, Nathan (Box 3)
  - Baraka, Imamu Amiri (Box 3)
  - Barber, Ione Morrison Rider, See Rider, Ione Morrison.
  - Barnett, Claude A. (Box 3)
  - Barrett, Lindsay (Box 3)
  - Barrett, William M. (Box 3)
  - Bass, Charlotta (Box 3)
  - Bass, George (Box 3)
  - Bayliss, John F. (Box 3)
  - Beacon Press (Box 3)
  - Beecher, John (Box 3)
  - Bellegarde, Dantes (Box 3)
  - Benet, William Rose, See The Saturday Review of Literature.
  - Bennett, Gwendolyn (Box 3)
  - Bennett College (Greensboro, N.C.) (Box 3)
  - Berkley, Constance E. G. (Box 3)
  - Bernfeld, Henri Marcel (Box 3)
  - Berry, Erick (Box 3)
  - Berry, Gail (Box 3)
  - Bethune, Lebert (Box 3)
  - Birth Control Federation of America, Inc., See Planned Parenthood Federation of America, Inc..
  - Blount, Mildred (Box 4)
  - Bluford, Lucile H. (Box 4)
  - Bond, Horace Mann (Box 4)
  - Bond, Julian (Box 4)
  - Bone, Robert (Box 4)
  - Bonner, Mary Graham (Box 4)
  - Bontemps, Charles-Auguste (Box 4)
  - Borome, Joseph Alfred (Box 4)
  - Bousfield, M. O. (Box 4)
  - Braithwaite, William Stanley (Box 4)
  - Brawley, Benjamin Griffith (Box 4)
  - Breen, Robert (Box 4)
  - Breman, Paul (Box 4)
  - British Broadcasting Corporation (Box 4)
  - Bromhall, Winifred (Box 4)
  - Brooks, Gwendolyn (Box 4)
  - Brooks, Helen Morgan (Box 4)
  - Brown, Benjamin A. (Box 4)
  - Brown, Elmer (Box 4)
  - Brown, Isabella Maria (Box 4)
  - Brown, Sterling Allen (Box 4)
  - Browning, Alice C. (Box 4)
  - Burden, Jean (Box 4)
  - Burley, Dan (Box 4)
  - Burns, Ben (Box 4)
    See also Ebony; Negro Digest.
  - Burns, Loretta Susie (Box 4)
  - Burnshaw, Stanley (Box 4)
  - Burrell, Natelkka E. (Box 4)
  - Burroughs, Margaret Taylor (Box 4)
  - Burrows, Vinie (Box 4)
  - Buster, Greene B. (Box 4)
  - Butcher, Philip (Box 4)
  - Byrd, James W. (Box 4)
  - Bynner, Witter (Box 4)
  - C, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Cahnman, Werner Jacob (Box 4)
  - Cain, Stith Malone (Box 4)
  - Campbell, Elmer Simms (Box 4)
  - Campbell, S. Brunson (Box 4)
  - Canaday, Nicholas (Box 4)
  - Canady, Hortense (Box 4)
  - Carew, Jan R. (Box 4)
  - Carlson, Julie Ann (Box 4)
  - Carrere, Mentis (Box 4)
  - Carter, Elmer A. (Box 4)
  - Cason, John Walter (Box 4)
  - Catholic Adult Education Center (Chicago, Ill.) (Box 4)
  - Cayton, Horace Roscoe (Box 4)
  - Les Cenelles Society of Arts and Letters (New Orleans, La.) (Box 4)
  - Chandler, Len (Box 5)
  - Chapman, Abraham (Box 5)
  - Chaput, Donald (Box 5)
  - Chesnutt, Helen M. (Box 5)
  - The Chicago Defender (Box 5)
  - Chicago Public Library (Box 5)
  - The Chicago Sun (Box 5)
  - Chicago Tribune (Box 5)
  - Chilton Books (Box 5)
  - Christian, Marcus Bruce, 1941-1963; undated; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Clarke, John Henrik (Box 5)
  - Clifton, Lucille (Box 5)
  - Cobb, William Montague (Box 5)
  - Cole, Robert A. (Box 5)
    See also Writings: Miscellaneous: "Young King Cole: a Boy Who Earned a Fortune".
  - Collins, Leslie M., 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Columbia University (Box 5)
  - Commins, Saxe (Box 5)
  - Committee for Mass Education in Race Relations, See Dodson, Owen.
  - Common Ground (Box 5)
  - Conroy, Jack, 1942-1957; 6 folders (Box 5)
  - Conroy, Jack, 1958-1968; undated; 6 folders (Box 6)
  - Cooper, Alvin (Box 6)
  - Cooper, Wayne F. (Box 6)
  - Cornish, Sam (Box 6)
  - Council on Interracial Books for Children, Inc. (Box 6)
  - Cowen, Joseph Robert (Box 6)
  - Crews, Judson (Box 6)
  - The Crisis (Box 6)
  - Cullen, Countee, 1942-1945; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Cullen, Ida Mae Roberson (Box 6)
  - Cuney, [William] Waring (Box 6)
  - Curtiss, Mina Stein Kirstein (Box 6)
  - Curtwright, Wesley (Box 6)
  - Czechoslovak Theatrical and Literary Agency, See DILIA.
  - D (Box 6)
  - Dabney, Wendell Phillips (Box 6)
  - Dalton, Henry (Box 6)
  - Danner, Margaret (Box 6)
  - Daughtry, Willa Estelle (Box 6)
  - Davis, Arthur Paul (Box 6)
  - Davis, Frank Marshall (Box 6)
  - Davis, Griff (Box 6)
  - Davis, John P., See Phelps-Stokes Fund.
  - Davis, Ossie, See Du Bois Memorial Committee.
  - Davis, Robert A. (Box 6)
  - Davis, Toussaint L. (Box 6)
    See also John Street Baptist Church (Worcester, Mass.).
  - Dawson, William Levi (Box 6)
  - [John] Day Company, Inc. (Box 6)
  - De Hartog, Jan (Box 6)
  - Delaware State College (Box 6)
  - Demby, William (Box 6)
  - Detroit Alumni Club of Fisk University (Box 6)
  - Detroit Children's Book Fair (1961) (Box 6)
  - Detroit Federation of Teachers (Box 6)
  - Detroit Fisk Alumni Club, See Detroit Alumni Club of Fisk University.
  - Dickinson, Donald C. (Box 6)
  - Dickinson, Elizabeth M. (Box 6)
  - DILIA (Box 6)
  - Dillard University (Box 6)
  - Dodd, Mead & Company, 1941-1973; undated; 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Dodson, Owen, 1944-1963; undated; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Domino, Ruth (Box 7)
  - Donahey, Mary D. (Box 7)
  - Dorsey, Thomas A. (Box 7)
  - Doubleday & Company, Inc. (Box 7)
  - Doubleday, Doran and Company, Inc., See Doubleday & Company, Inc..
  - Douglas, Aaron and Alta (Box 7)
  - Dover, Cedric (Box 7)
  - Dramatists' Guild (Box 7)
  - Dreer, Herman (Box 7)
  - Dryden Press, Inc., See Burnshaw, Stanley.
  - DuBois, Rachel Davis (Box 7)
  - Du Bois, Shirley Graham (Box 7)
  - Du Bois, William Edward Burghardt - 1927-1961 see also, 2 folders (Box 7)
    See also Writings: Books: 100 Years of Negro Freedom, Writings: Miscellaneous: "The Free and the Fatherless": W. E. B. Du Bois Section.
  - Du Bois Memorial Committee (Box 7)
  - Dumas, Henry (Box 7)
  - Dunbar, Rudolph (Box 7)
  - Duncan, Anne McKay (Box 7)
  - Duncan, Rea Lubar (Box 7)
  - Dunham, Katherine (Box 7)
  - Durem, Dorothy (Mrs. Ray) (Box 7)
  - Durham, Richard (Box 7)
  - Du Sable High School (Chicago) (Box 7)
  - [E. P.] Dutton and Co., Inc. (Box 7)
  - E (Box 7)
  - Ebony (Box 7)
  - Edman, Marion (Box 7)
  - Edmonds, Randolph (Box 7)
  - Educational Services Incorporated (Cambridge, Mass.) (Box 7)
  - Edwards, Colin D. (Box 7)
  - Edwards, Thyra (Box 7)
  - Eisenberg, Bernard (Box 8)
  - Eldridge, Paul (Box 8)
  - Ellis, Ethel Bontemps (Box 8)
  - Ellison, James and Virginia (Box 8)
  - Ellison, Ralph and Fanny (Box 8)
  - Emanuel, James A. (Box 8)
  - Embree, Edwin R. (Box 8)
    See also [Julius] Rosenwald Fund.
  - Encyclopaedia Britannica (Box 8)
  - English, Gladys (Box 8)
  - Enright, James O. (Box 8)
  - Epelle, Sam, "Meet Nigeria" manuscript (Box 8)
  - [Paul S.] Erikson, Inc. (Box 8)
  - Establishment Theatre Company, Inc. (New York, N.Y.), See Aaron, Stephen.
  - Estes, David E. (Box 8)
  - Evans, Eva Knox (Box 8)
  - Evans, Mari (Box 8)
  - Evansville (Ind.) Public Library (Box 8)
  - F (Box 8)
  - Fabio, Sarah Webster (Box 8)
  - Fabre, Michel (Box 8)
  - Fagin, Nathan Bryllion (Box 8)
  - Faulkner, William J. (Box 8)
  - Fauset, Arthur Huff (Box 8)
  - Fauset, Jessie Redmon (Box 8)
  - Ferguson, Blanche E. (Box 8)
  - Ferris, Helen Josephine (Box 8)
  - Field, Marshall (Box 8)
  - Fields, Julia (Box 8)
  - Fisk University
    - Printed material, 1942-1972; undated; 9 folders (Box 8, 9)
    - Fisk University Centennial Writers Conference: "The Image of the Negro in American Literature", 22-24 Apr. 1966; lectures (Box 9)
  - Folkways Records, See Asch, Moses.
  - Follett Publishing Company (Box 9)
  - Foner, Philip S., See International Publishers.
  - Ford, Nick Aaron (Box 9)
  - Ford Foundation (Box 9)
  - Forgue, Norman W. (Box 9)
  - Frank, Waldo (Box 9)
  - Frederick, John Towner (Box 9)
  - Free Library of Philadelphia (Box 9)
  - Freeman, Carol (Box 9)
  - Friends of Literature (Chicago, Ill.) (Box 9)
  - Friendship Press (Box 9)
  - Fuller, Hoyt W. (Box 9)
  - G (Box 9)
  - Galantiere, Lewis (Box 9)
  - Gannett, Lewis (Box 9)
  - Garber, Ethel (Box 10)
  - Gates, Doris (Box 10)
  - George Peabody College for Teachers (Box 10)
  - Georgia State Department of Education (Box 10)
  - Gibbs, James L. (Box 10)
  - Gilbert, Lon (Box 10)
  - Gilbert, Zack (Box 10)
  - Gilden, Bert and Katya (Box 10)
  - Gilpin, Patrick J. (Box 10)
  - Ginn and Company (Box 10)
  - Gleason, Ralph J. (Box 10)
  - Goodwill Book Club (Memphis, Tenn.) (Box 10)
  - Gorlier, Claudio (Box 10)
  - Goss, Margaret Taylor see, See Burroughs, Margaret Taylor
  - Graham, Rudy B. (Box 10)
  - Graham, Shirley, See Du Bois, Shirley Graham.
  - Granger, Lester B. (Box 10)
  - Green, Archie (Box 10)
  - Greene, Jay E. (Box 10)
  - Gregory, Yvonne (Box 10)
  - Grolier, Inc., 1961-1966; undated; 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Gross, Edward (Box 10)
  - Gross, Theodore L. (Box 10)
  - Grosset & Dunlap, Inc. (Box 10)
  - Grove, Thurman and Mary (Box 10)
  - [John Simon] Guggenheim Memorial Foundation (Box 10)
  - Gysin, Brion (Box 10)
  - H (Box 10)
  - Haines, Madge (Box 10)
  - Hair, Paul Edward Hedley (Box 10)
  - Hale, Frank W. (Box 10)
  - Hall, Theresa H. (Box 10)
  - Hampton Institute (Box 10)
  - Handley-Taylor, Geoffrey (Box 10)
  - Handy, William Christopher, 1939-1940; 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Handy, William Christopher, 1941-1958; undated; 3 folders (Box 11)
  - Hanrahan, Virginia (Box 11)